@纪录片之家字幕组
Spain. Al-Andalus. Iberia, Hispania.
西班牙  安达卢斯  伊比利亚  伊伯利亚
www.jlpzj.net
Many names for the same country.
都是这个国家的名字
翻译 lsmlive
Spain has had more diversity
西班牙比西欧其它国家
and more manifestations than any other country in western Europe.
更具有多元性和代表性
It's a peninsula almost surrounded by water.
这座半岛几乎四面环水
That's its blessing and its curse.
这既是福祉  也是诅咒
The road to Spain has always been the sea, from the South.
进出西班牙长期都靠南方的海路
From 3000 BC onwards, the great traders of the Mediterranean -
自公元前3000年起  地中海的大商人们
the Greeks and Phoenicians came here
希腊人和腓尼基人来到这里
attracted by its fertile plains,
此地有诱人的肥沃平原
and its mines that brought forth gold and silver, tin and copper.
还有丰富的金银锡铜矿藏
Spain is European, yet it looks to Africa.
西班牙坐落欧洲  又与非洲相望
Forged by rulers, armies, peoples and faiths
她由统治者  军队  人民和信仰所锻造
more exotic than elsewhere in the West.
且比西方其它地方更具外来风情
Spain's position at the extremity of Europe
西班牙地处欧洲边缘
has made it the borderland and the battlefield
欧陆上的许多势力
of the continent's many different influences.
在其边疆征伐不断
It's joined to Europe and yet only 14km from Africa.
她接壤欧洲  又距非洲仅14千米
Everything here reflects its unique meshing
这里的一切都体现了犹太人
of the Jewish, Muslim and Christian cultures.
穆斯林  基督教文化的独特融合
That's what makes Spain so unique.
这也是西班牙如此独特的原因
I come both as historian and traveller.
我将以历史学家和旅游者的角度
To explore who and what shaped the soul of Spain.
来探索西班牙之魂如何铸就
From Paganism, Islam and Catholicism,
从异教  伊斯兰教到天主教
via dictatorship, to today's democracy.
从独裁专制到今日的民主制度
I'll tell the story from the Atlantic to the Mediterranean.
我将讲述从大西洋到地中海的故事
I start in the South.
我将从南方开始
Cadiz, Spain's oldest living city.
加的斯  西班牙现存最古老的城市
Seville, Andalusia's Catholic capital.
塞维利亚  安达卢西亚的天主教首府
Gibraltar, Spain's gateway.
直布罗陀  西班牙的门户
Cordoba, capital of the Islamic Caliphate.
科尔多瓦  伊斯兰哈里发的首都
And Granada, home of the Alhambra.
还有格拉纳达  阿尔罕布拉宫所在
I'll find the hidden corners, the stories we don't know,
我将遍访 偏僻之暗角  未知之伕事
the secrets, the titans who created the nation.
隐没之秘闻  立国之伟人
For centuries, this was Europe's Wild West.
几个世纪来  这里都是欧洲的狂野西部
Where caliphs and kings created palaces and cities,
哈里发和国王们于此建起宫殿与城市
where they fought wars of annihilation.
他们也于此征战湮灭
Here, a concubine could become a queen.
在这里  一位妃妾变成一代女王
Here, a naked princess sparked a decisive invasion.
在这里  一位赤裸的公主引发了一场决定性入侵
Blood and gold, beauty and death, persecution and tolerance.
鲜血与黄金  美丽和死亡  迫害与宽容
This is the story of the making of Spain.
这便是铸就西班牙的故事
鲜血与黄金 铸就西班牙
西蒙·蒙蒂菲奥里
第一集
征服
The Atlantic city of Cadiz is my first stop.
加的斯的大西洋城是我的第一站
More than 2,000 years ago,
2000多年前
this was a colony of the Phoenician city of Carthage
这里是迦太基的腓尼基人殖民地
in today's Tunisia.
隶属于现在的突尼斯
In 237 BC, one of history's most famous figures was brought here.
公元前237年  史上赫赫有名的一位人物被带来了这里
As a ten-year-old boy, the young Hannibal came to Cadiz.
仅有10岁的汉尼拔来到了加的斯
And from here, his father, Hamilcar, would conquer most of Spain
其父 哈米尔卡 将从这里开始征服西班牙大部
as a new Carthaginian empire.
建起一个新的迦太基帝国
Now Spain became the battlefield
现在西班牙成了战场
for one of the great set-piece
献演了一场精彩的
西蒙·蒙蒂菲奥里
imperial rivalries of the ancient world.
古代帝国攻防战
The Phoenicians came from the city of Tyre.
腓尼基人从提尔城而来
（又译苏尔、泰尔、提洛、推罗）
They spread out throughout the Mediterranean.
他们遍布地中海沿岸
And the greatest city they founded was Carthage.
他们所建的最大城市便是迦太基
The Carthaginians started to found an empire
迦太基人开始建起了一个帝国
and that brought them into conflict with
这就给他们带来了跟地中海
the other rising power of the Mediterranean.
另一股新兴势力的冲突
Rome.
罗马
Hannibal was born into a family already at war.
汉尼拔降生时  其家族已陷入战争
Their name, Barca, meant thunderbolt.
家族姓氏  巴卡  即有迅雷之意
When his father conquered Spain as his next move against Rome,
当父亲要征服西班牙以对抗罗马时
Hannibal begged to go with him.
汉尼拔便求着要跟去
He was 19 when his father died.
他19岁时  父亲离世了
Gradually, he would assume command of his father's empire.
渐渐地  他将子承父业  执掌帝国
The coming war needed the blessing of the Gods
接下来的战争需要众神的祝福
and I've come to meet one.
而我正要去会见其中一神
Isn't it a breathtaking thought?
想想便很奇妙
That as we look at this,
此时我们所看着的这个
Hannibal himself once gazed upon this very statue.
便是汉尼拔曾凝视过的同一尊雕像
This Cadiz museum contains some of
加的斯的这间博物馆藏有一些
the priceless treasures from Hannibal's time.
来自汉尼拔时期的无价珍宝
And this figurine of the god Melqart
这座神祗美刻尔的雕像
once stood on the Island of Sancti Petri.
曾矗立于圣彼得里岛
And that's where I'm going,
而我正要去那儿
a few miles south of Cadiz,
从加的斯往南走几英里
just like Hannibal did.
就像汉尼拔做过的一样
In 218 BC, Hannibal, now 29,
公元前218年  29岁的汉尼拔
travelled here to Melqart's temple.
来到此地拜访美刻尔神庙
He had a plan of astonishing ambition
他的壮志伟业
that required Melqart's blessing.
需要美刻尔的祝福
Melqart was the God of Tyre,
美刻尔是提尔城的守护神
mother city of the Carthaginians.
提尔则是迦太基人的母城
And he appears in the Jewish Bible as the god Baal.
美刻尔在犹太圣经中被称作巴力神
It was said that Melqart was unfaithful to his wife,
传说美刻尔对妻子不忠
who castrated him and killed him,
于是被妻子先阉后杀
at which he was miraculously brought back to life.
然而他却奇迹般地起死回生
His resurrection made him a symbol of vim, vigour, power and virility.
于是他也成为了精气活力  阳刚力量的象征
Temple complexes like this were central to ancient life.
这样的神庙群是古代的生活中心
There were human sacrifices.
活人祭祀就在这里举行
Priests cut the throats of bulls
祭司将公牛割喉
and splashed blood on the naked bodies of supplicants.
并把血泼向裸体的祈愿者
As you can see, there's nothing here except seagulls
你可以看到  这里只有一堆海鸥
and this deserted 18th-century fort.
以及18世纪的荒废堡垒
But this was once one of the richest,
但这里曾是整个古代世界
grandest and most famous temple shrines
最为富饶  宏伟和著名的
in the entire ancient world.
神庙圣地
It was a critical moment.
这是个关键时刻
Carthaginian Spain challenged
迦太基夺下西班牙威胁到了
Roman mastery of the Mediterranean.
罗马对地中海的掌控
That meant a new Roman war against Carthage.
罗马与迦太基终有一战
Here at Sancti Petri, Hannibal consulted the Oracle of Melqart.
在圣彼得里岛  汉尼拔请示美刻尔神谕
Hannibal took an oath to destroy Rome.
汉尼拔发誓要灭掉罗马
He said, "I swear to arrest the destiny of Rome with fire and steel."
他说  我发誓要用烈火和钢铁终结罗马国运
Rather than waiting for Rome to attack him,
未等罗马来袭
Hannibal would take the fight to the enemy.
汉尼拔先发制人
It would be one of the most audacious military campaigns of antiquity.
这将是古代最大胆的军事行动之一
Harnessing Spain and Africa,
倚靠着西班牙和非洲
Hannibal would attack Italy.
汉尼拔将进攻意大利
Here in Cadiz, Hannibal mustered a huge army of 60,000.
在加的斯这里  汉尼拔集结了6万大军
Including Spanish spearmen and African cavalry.
其中就有西班牙长枪兵和非洲骑兵
And 40 war elephants, the ultimate prestige weapon.
以及终极杀器  40头战象
In 217, Hannibal marched this huge army,
公元前217年  汉尼拔指挥这只大军
from Spain, across the south of France,
从西班牙出发  途经法国南部
over the Alps - including all his elephants -
带着大象翻过阿尔卑斯山
and then down into Italy.
驱入意大利
He headed for Rome.
他要直取罗马
Hannibal's campaign would bring Rome to the edge of defeat.
汉尼拔的行动本可使罗马濒于溃败
Victory over Rome would change the entire history of Europe.
战胜罗马将改变整个欧洲历史
Knowing what we know now about the invincibility
我们都知道将来的罗马帝国
of the future Roman Empire,
多么地所向披靡
Hannibal's adventure looks reckless, if not absurd.
汉尼拔的冒险不算荒谬的话  也可谓鲁莽了
But Hannibal was a child of the Hellenistic
但汉尼拔成长于
or Greek culture in the Mediterranean,
地中海的希腊化时代
unleashed by his hero, Alexander the Great.
受到亚历山大大帝事迹的鼓舞
And compared to Alexander's exploits in the East,
与亚历山大的东征相比
this invasion of Italy might be child's play.
这场入侵意大利可能有点小巫见大巫了
It was Rome's supreme crisis.
但它却是罗马的最大危机
Hannibal repeatedly defeated the Roman armies
汉尼拔连连击败罗马军队
and at Cannae, he routed them.
并在坎尼伏击了他们
And yet, even as Hannibal was closing in, Rome did not fall.
然而即便汉尼拔不断逼近  罗马仍未陷落
The Romans prayed and then they rallied.
罗马人祈祷完毕  继续集结
Cato the Elder, one of their statesmen, repeatedly declared,
罗马政治家 老加图 一再宣称
"Carthago delenda est"
迦太基必须被消灭
- Carthage must be annihilated.
即 迦太基必须被消灭
And now, they found a general almost
而现在  他们发现了一位
as sublime a strategist as Hannibal himself.
谋略不逊于汉尼拔的将军
And he would take the war to Hannibal's Spain,
他将把战争带到汉尼拔的西班牙
just as Hannibal had brought the war to Rome.
以回敬汉尼拔把战火烧向罗马
This was the moment that the Romans became Romans.
罗马人的厉害就在这时体现出来了
A few miles north of Seville in the heart of Andalusia,
在安达卢西亚中心的塞维利亚往北几英里处
the vicious blood feud of Carthage and Rome would be decided.
血海深仇的迦太基和罗马将一决胜负
In 206 BC, the two sides met right here in a battle.
公元前206年  双方对峙于此
The winners would rule Europe for the next 700 years.
胜者将会继续统治欧洲700年
The Roman commander was Publius Cornelius Scipio.
罗马的指挥官是普布里乌斯·科涅利乌斯·西庇阿
It was said in Rome that only Scipio would dare
据说在罗马只有西庇阿敢于
to take on the Carthaginian Empire.
挑战迦太基帝国
Both his father and his uncle had been killed in battle
他的父亲和叔叔都死于汉尼拔家族
by Hannibal's family.
挑起的战端中
So, for Scipio, it was personal.
所以这是西庇阿的私仇
Just as Hannibal had vowed to destroy Rome,
正如汉尼拔发誓要灭掉罗马一样
Scipio vowed to destroy Carthage.
西庇阿也发誓要摧毁迦太基
And his plan was as bold as it was simple.
而他的计划既大胆又简单
While the brilliant Hannibal fought on in Italy for over a decade,
当卓越的汉尼拔在意大利征战十多年时
Spain was defended by his feuding, disunited brothers.
守卫西班牙的是与其不和的弟弟
Scipio slipped into Spain with his small army.
西庇阿带着小股队伍溜进西班牙
Military historian Saul David is here to tell me
军事史学家索尔·大卫将会告诉我
how Scipio faced the Carthaginians
西庇阿是如何在伊里帕这里
right here at Ilipa.
迎战迦太基人的
We're right on the spot of that battle.
我们所处的正是曾经的战场
Tell me what happened that day?
跟我说说那天发生了什么
To give you an idea of numbers,
先让你有个数字的概念
the Romans have about 50,000 and the Carthaginians 75,000,
罗马人约有5万人  迦太基人约有7.5万人
so they're heavily outnumbered.
所以他们在数量上严重不敌
And for the two or three days prior to the actual battle itself,
离真正开战还有两三天时
Scipio sets his army up in a very traditional way.
西庇阿用很传统的阵法来布兵
So his strongest forces are in the centre,
最强的部队位于中间
his Roman and Italian legions, and his allies,
而罗马和意大利兵团  以及盟军
who he can't really rely on, are on the flank.
他都不能深信  故放之侧翼
But on the day of the battle itself, he changes all of that.
但到了开战那天  他将其完全变了个样
He orders the army out very early in the morning,
他一大早就命令部队行动
he gets them into position before
在迦太基人还没反应过来前
the Carthaginians are ready to respond
他就让部队就位了
and he changes his formation
他改变了先前的阵型
so that his elite forces are actually now on the flanks.
好让精英部队变到侧翼去
And this allows him to advance in a very unusual way
这就使得他的推进方式非常独特
with a concave formation, so that his best troops are on the side.
中间下凹  两边则是他最精锐的部队
And in a nutshell, cos you could go on about this battle
关于这场战斗有很详细的记叙
in great detail,
简单来说
it means that the strongest Carthaginian troops
就是迦太基最强的部队
never actually get to fight until late on during the battle.
直到战斗末期才加入战斗
So how did the elephants,
那么那些大象呢
the Carthaginian elephants perform on the day?
迦太基人的大象有什么表现吗
You've got to imagine a scenario where once the battle starts,
你可以想象一下  战斗开始之后
the elephants don't see friend or foe.
大象就分不清敌友了
They've got their guides, as it were,
虽然还是有人在驾驶它们
but everyone else is fair game.
但其他人就都是无差别的
And if you get in the way of a war elephant,
只要你挡在了战象的面前
particularly one who's been stung by a few javelins being thrown at him,
要是那头象刚好还被飞来的枪矛给刺了几下
he's going to trample anyone.
那它就会到处碾压
And a four-tonne beast treading on you
一只4吨重的动物踩到你
is going to leave a bit of a sticky mess underneath.
你就成了一堆黏糊糊的肉酱了
So, you can see that the use of the Carthaginian war elephant
所以迦太基人使用战象
was as much of an own goal as it was a success.
更多的只是弄巧成拙
Scipio was victorious.
西庇阿取得了胜利
Spain became a province of Europe,
西班牙成了欧洲的一个省
not Africa
而非隶属非洲
- of Rome, not Carthage.
它属于罗马  而非迦太基
He built this, the city of Italica,
西庇阿在战场旁边建起了
next to the battlefield,
这座意大利卡城
for the veterans of his victory.
以安置战胜的退伍老兵
Control of the peninsula gave Scipio
控制了半岛让西庇阿
a springboard to attack North Africa.
有了跳板去攻击北非
This amazing mosaic here in Italica
意大利卡的这幅精美马赛克
tells the story of Scipio's
讲述的就是西庇阿
wars against Carthage.
对迦太基的战争
In 204, Scipio crossed to Africa, taking the war to Carthage.
前204年  西庇阿渡海前往北非攻打迦太基
As he approached,
随着西庇阿来袭
the Carthaginians recalled Hannibal from Italy.
迦太基人把汉尼拔从意大利召回
He rushed back, but Scipio defeated him.
他赶回来后  还是被西庇阿打败了
The city fell.
迦太基陷落
Scipio was rewarded with a title,
西庇阿赢得了一个称号
Africanus,
非洲征服者
but his haughtiness won him many enemies.
但他的自傲使他树敌众多
He was prosecuted and exiled to his estates.
他被起诉并流放回自己的庄园
As for Hannibal, he roamed the East,
而汉尼拔则流亡到东方
enemy number one, pursued by Roman agents.
罗马人一直追捕着这一头号大敌
Finally, he committed suicide.
最后  他自杀身亡了
As for Carthage, ultimately it was wiped off the map.
而迦太基最终也不复存在
Now it was Rome's turn to colonise Spain.
现在轮到罗马来殖民西班牙了
The Romans loved Hispania, Roman Spain.
罗马人喜爱伊伯利亚  罗马治下的西班牙
They found it almost more Italian than Italy.
他们发现这里比意大利还要意大利
Here, life was good and they could make great fortunes in fish paste,
这里生活美好  鱼酱 橄榄油和葡萄酒
olive oil and wine.
利润丰厚
In 98 AD,
公元98年
they chose as Emperor a general from around here, Italica.
他们选了个意大利卡的将军来做罗马皇帝
His name was Trajan.
他就是 图拉真
Competent and honest, he was a formidable soldier
他德才兼备  是个受敬仰的战士
and an outstanding ruler.
也是个杰出的统治者
He was actually voted the title Optimus,
他被授予 最优秀者 的称号
the best, and he was.
可谓实至名归
His successor Hadrian,
他的继任者 哈德良
also from here, Italica,
也出自意大利卡这儿
was probably the most accomplished man
他可能是罗马所有皇帝中
ever to rule the Roman Empire.
成就最为非凡的
Everything he did, he did properly.
他所做的一切都妥善得当
He created the Pantheon in Rome.
他在罗马建造了万神殿
And here, he improved Italica enormously.
他也对意大利卡贡献巨大
Marcus Aurelius the Philosopher Emperor,
马可·奥勒留  哲学家皇帝
was also from a Spanish Roman family.
他也出自西班牙裔的罗马家庭
It's ironic, isn't it?
这挺讽刺的是吧
That the three greatest Roman emperors
帝国顶峰时期的三位
at the Empire's zenith
最伟大的罗马皇帝
were from Roman Spain.
都来自罗马治下的西班牙
Hispania became the food bowl and the winery of the empire.
伊伯利亚成了帝国的粮仓和酒庄
Producing the essentials and the delicacies of Roman life.
产出着罗马人的生活原料和美味佳肴
Spanish olive oil and wine were sent around the Mediterranean
畅销地中海沿岸的西班牙橄榄油和葡萄酒
in amphorae just like these.
就装在这种双耳土罐里
But there was a problem,
但有个问题是
which neither the Carthaginians nor after them,
迦太基人和后来的
the Romans, could solve.
罗马人都解决不了的
The amphorae could only be used once
这种双耳土罐只能一次性使用
and after that, the pottery was tainted.
然后它就会受污染变质
At the height of Roman Hispania,
在罗马伊伯利亚的巅峰期
so many were being exported to Rome -
许多这种罐子出口到了罗马
as many as 54 million
共有5400万之多
- that their debris formed a heap.
罐子的残骸就堆积起来
And the heap became a mountain.
最终堆成了一座山
And Mount Testaccio is still there to this day.
它便是今天的泰斯塔西奥山
The used amphorae, transported from Spain to Rome,
从西班牙运到罗马的双耳土罐
were broken into pieces
被砸成了碎片
and then sprinkled with lime
再撒上石灰
to neutralise the smell of rancid olive oil.
来中和掉橄榄油的酸臭味
The centre of Roman life here in Italica was its amphitheatre.
意大利卡的罗马生活中心便是露天剧场
One of the largest and best preserved
其中一座最大且保存最完好的
after Rome's Colosseum.
仅次于罗马斗兽场
It could seat 25,000 people.
它可以容纳2.5万人
In around 50 AD,
公元50年前后
this arena became the focus for a sport
这座竞技场因一种运动而成为焦点
that later became the emblem of a nation.
这一运动随后成为了一个国家的象征
In a moment of imperial whimsy,
帝国有段反复无常的时期
the stuttering Emperor Claudius
口吃皇帝 克劳狄乌斯
banned all gladiatorial fights in Spain.
禁止了西班牙的所有角斗
And these were replaced with contests of exotic beasts.
代之以奇异的野兽搏斗
The lions and the tigers were all kept down here in these pits.
狮子老虎都被关在底下这里
And amongst them were the local Spanish bulls,
其中还有当地的西班牙公牛
which were then sent up into the amphitheatre
它们被送来露天竞技场
to be viciously slaughtered to the crowds' delight.
被残忍宰杀以取悦观众
This was the beginning of Spanish bullfighting.
这便是西班牙斗牛的开端
Rome's traditional Gods were often fused with
罗马传统的神往往糅杂了
foreign deities who became fashionable.
外来的流行神
One blood-saturated fertility cult
一种血腥的生殖崇拜
may link the Carthaginian past with the Spanish future.
将迦太基的过往与西班牙的未来联系起来
Attis, a comely shepherd boy,
阿提斯  这位俊秀的牧羊少年
channelled the story of Melqart before him.
联起了早先的美刻尔的故事
He too was castrated by his jealous lover,
他也被心生妒意的爱人所阉
or some said castrated himself and bled to death.
也有说是他自行阉割  流血致死
But he bounced back in an unforgettable way
但他却惊人地死而复生
as the ultimate symbol of virility for his frenzied cult followers.
于是狂热分子视其为生殖力的终极象征
They would cavort, splattering themselves with blood,
他们会腾空跳起  血洒一身
flagellating themselves, biting each other,
鞭打自己  撕咬对方
and as the ultimate gesture of devotion,
最终的献身方式
castrating themselves.
便是自行阉割
It's said that these traditions may be echoed today
据说这些传统至今仍未消亡
in the self-flagellating Catholic brotherhoods
西班牙的自虐天主教兄弟会
that are still going on in Spain.
还有这些传统
Hadrian, the Spanish-born emperor
哈德良  这位西班牙裔皇帝
who beautified Italica,
他曾美化意大利卡
unwittingly changed Spain.
也曾无意间改变了西班牙
When, in 132 AD,
公元132年
his persecution of the Jews in Jerusalem
他在耶路撒冷对犹太人的迫害
provoked a revolt.
激起了反抗
Hadrian rushed troops to Judea to crush the rebellion.
哈德良急令军队去镇压叛乱
But the Jews under their commander, the Prince of Israel,
但犹太人在以色列王子
Simon Bar Kokhba,
巴尔·科赫巴的领导下
managed to wipe out several Roman legions
还是消灭了一些罗马军团
before they were finally crushed.
然后才被镇压下去
Hadrian had 500,000 Jews slaughtered
哈德良屠杀了50万犹太人
and they were banned in perpetuity from their beloved Jerusalem.
犹太人被永久禁止进入其敬爱的耶路撒冷
But many of them came to settle here in Spain,
于是他们中的许多人来到西班牙定居
to found a community
形成了一个社区
named after the Hebrew word for Spain, Saffarad,
名为 Saffarad  希伯来语  意为西班牙
hence the Sephadic Jews.
这才有了塞法迪犹太人
Even today,
即便到了今天
the Jews in Spain call themselves
西班牙的犹太人也说自己是
"the exile from Jerusalem in Spain".
"从耶路撒冷流亡到西班牙的"
Out of the Jewish disaster,
解决了犹太灾难后
a new religion emerged and spread fast.
一种新的宗教出现并迅速传播
It would challenge the Roman empire from within.
它将由内部对罗马帝国发起挑战
I'm leaving Italica
我正离开意大利卡
and heading a few miles south to Seville.
要往南几英里到塞维利亚
To find out what happened when a new faith of Christianity
我要探寻当新的基督信仰面对
confronted the old paganism of Rome.
古老的罗马异教时都发生了什么
Seville, now dominated by Catholic monuments,
塞维利亚现在满是天主教遗迹
was then called Hispalis.
它曾叫做西帕里斯
Archaeology reveals it was a typical Roman city.
考古表明这曾是座典型的罗马城市
This is the story of Justa and Rufina,
这是有关 胡斯塔 和 鲁菲娜 的故事
later the patron saints of Seville.
她们后来成了塞维利亚的守护神
They were sisters, devout Christians,
她们是虔诚的基督徒姐妹
and much admired for their work as potters.
因其陶匠工作而颇受尊敬
In 287 AD,
公元287年
the city prefect Diogenianus
市长 迪欧基纳尔斯
ordered all pots must be offered to Venus.
下令所有的陶器都要献给维纳斯
This edict was almost certainly part
这项法令几乎可以肯定是皇帝
of Emperor Diocletian's policy
戴克里先 政策的一部分
to reinvigorate Roman religion.
其旨在重振罗马宗教
It was also a direct affront to Christianity.
这也是对基督教的直接冒犯
Justa and Rufina made a stand.
胡斯塔 和 鲁菲娜  坚决不从
Justa and Rufina ran the best pottery in Seville.
胡斯塔 和 鲁菲娜  有着塞维利亚最好的制陶厂
But these wholesome Christians refused to let their pottery
但是这些虔诚的基督徒拒绝拿自己的陶器
be used in a pagan festival for the goddess Venus.
去在一个异教节日上献给女神维纳斯
So good was their pottery,
她们的陶器那么精美
and so essential,
那么至关重要
that the pagan crowd was outraged.
所以异教徒们愤怒了
They broke into the pottery
他们闯进制陶厂
and took the pots they needed for their pagan festival.
抢走异教节日所需要的陶器
The two sisters were outraged in their turn.
现在轮到这对姐妹愤怒了
They smashed a statue of Venus.
她们砸毁了一尊维纳斯的雕像
Now, sympathetic as I am to these pious young ladies,
现在我是非常地同情这些虔诚的年轻女士
this was nothing less than a brazen bid for martyrdom.
因为此举无异于是自寻死路
And their prayers were indeed answered.
果不其然
Diogenianus arrested them immediately
迪欧基纳尔斯 马上逮捕了她们
and they were horribly tortured with hooks and fire.
她们被用钩子和烈火残酷折磨
When she was almost dead,
在奄奄一息的时候
Justa was thrown down a 100ft well,
胡斯塔被投入一口100英尺深的井
where she perished.
然后丧生
As for Rufina,
至于 鲁菲娜
she was saved for the lions.
她则要面对狮子
As the wild beasts were unleashed upon Rufina,
当狮子们被放出来时
the crowd bayed in anticipation.
众人期待得大叫
But instead of eating her,
但狮子们没有吃她
they licked her wounds.
而是舔了舔她的伤口
The Christians saw this as a miracle
基督徒们认为这是个奇迹
but Diogenianus was unimpressed.
但迪欧基纳尔斯不为所动
He had her strangled, beheaded
他把她勒死  然后斩首
and then burned.
最后烧毁
But the Christians had their first martyr.
但基督徒们有了他们的首位殉道者
Within 30 years,
在30年内
the Roman Empire itself had converted to Christianity.
罗马帝国便改信基督教了
Yet it was disintegrating.
然而帝国正在崩溃中
When Rome fell in 476 AD,
公元476年  罗马灭亡
Spain was at the mercy of invading tribes of so-called Barbarians.
西班牙遭到了所谓蛮族部落的入侵和摆布
First came the Vandals,
首先来的是汪达尔人
who failed to hold the Peninsula for long.
他们很快就丢失了这块半岛
They left only one real legacy, their name.
他们留下的就只有他们的称呼
Andalusia, still the name for Southern Spain,
安达卢西亚  仍然是南西班牙的名称
comes from the Arabic Al-Andalus,
它源于阿拉伯语 安达卢斯
probably meaning "The land of the Vandals."
可能意思就是  "汪达尔人的土地"
Next, the Byzantine emperor Justinian
接下来  拜占庭皇帝查士丁尼
captured parts of Spain
夺取了西班牙部分
until his garrisons were overrun by the Visigoths.
后来他的驻军被西哥特人所击败
Ferocious in war, they were creative in peace.
西哥特人战时凶猛  和平时富有创意
Visigoths usually feature
西哥特人在中世纪黑暗时代
as raping and pillaging axe men
通常被视作奸淫掳掠
of the Dark Ages.
挥着斧头的人
But when the Visigoths settled in Spain,
但当西哥特人在西班牙定居下来后
they produced sages, scholars
他们中也出现了圣贤  学者
as well as soldiers.
以及士兵
This school, like many others in Spain,
这所学校和西班牙其它许多学校一样
is named after St Isidore,
都叫做 圣伊西多
Visigothic Bishop of Seville,
他是塞维利亚的西哥特人主教
who refined and adapted Roman law
曾完善和调整了罗马法
to create a united, Christian Spain.
从而创建了一个团结的基督教西班牙
Much later,
再多往后一点儿
Visigothic Spain became
西哥特下的西班牙成为了
the prototype for Catholic monarchy.
天主教君主制的雏形
Ruling for two centuries,
统治了两个世纪的
their kingdom would inspire Spanish rulers
西哥特人的王国一直到20世纪都激励着
right up until the 20th century.
西班牙统治者们
Downstream from Seville is the river port of Santa Maria.
塞维利亚下游是圣玛丽亚的河港
This stretch of water is known as the River of the Dead.
这片水域是著名的死亡之河
With good reason.
它名副其实
This river is the place where Visigothic Spain died.
这条河流正是西哥特西班牙的终结之地
This is where its last king, Roderick, was killed.
西哥特末代国王 罗德里克 被杀于此
And it was a moment that changed the entire destiny of Spain.
这也改变了整个西班牙的命运
The Visigoths matter as much for how they lost Spain
西哥特人夺取了西班牙
as for how they won it.
却也亲自失掉了西班牙
It all started with a beautiful naked girl.
一切都始于一名美丽的赤裸女子
Roderick, the King, was in the habit of spying upon Florinda,
国王罗德里克有到弗洛林达刺探侦察的习惯
the daughter of his nobleman Julian, while she was in her bath.
国王手下的贵族朱利安的女儿正在洗澡
One day, he ravished her.
国王奸污了她
She ran to her father, Julian, he rebelled.
于是她的父亲朱利安起而抗之
And here, on this river, at the River of the Dead,
就在这里  在这条死亡之河上
he met Roderick's forces and killed him.
他遇上了罗德里克一行  并将其杀死
Now, most Visigothic kings were assassinated.
至今多数的西哥特国王都被刺杀身亡
So there was no big deal in that.
所以这也算不得什么
But what mattered here was how he was killed.
但重要的是他如何被杀死
For Julian didn't just rebel,
朱利安不仅反叛了
he looked in this direction,
他还朝向这个方向
across the sea to North Africa for help.
向海外的北非求援
Julian summoned Islam.
朱利安叫来了伊斯兰
Far away in the deserts of Arabia,
在遥远的阿拉伯沙漠中
a new faith, a new revelation had arisen.
一种新的信仰  新的启示已经崛起
By the time he died in 632,
在632年离世之时
the Prophet Mohammed had united Arabia under the banners of Islam.
先知穆罕默德已经把阿拉伯凝聚在伊斯兰教下了
In the next 50 years, the Arab armies conquered a vast empire,
接下来50年  阿拉伯军队将征服建起一片广袤帝国
stretching from Iran all the way to Morocco,
一路从伊朗到摩洛哥
all ruled from Damascus by his successors,
都在大马士革的统治下
the commanders of the faithful, the Caliphs.
先知继承者是忠诚的指挥官  哈里发
The spectacular Arab conquests
恢弘的阿拉伯征服
brought Islam to the shores of the Moroccan coast,
把伊斯兰带到了摩洛哥海岸
just 14km from Spain.
此地距西班牙仅14千米
Julian called for help from the Governor of Tangiers.
朱利安求助于丹吉尔的总督
This was irresistible to an empire built on the fever of faith
对于一个狂热于信仰和战争的帝国来说
and the spoils of war.
这求援难以拒绝
This is where Islam arrived.
伊斯兰就是从这里来的
When we think of Gibraltar,
当提到直布罗陀时
we think of a part of Spain that isn't really Spanish.
我们便会觉得西班牙这地方可不怎么像是西班牙
A little piece of Britain in the Mediterranean,
这是地中海上的一小股英伦风
with red telephone kiosks, postboxes
有红色的电话亭和邮筒
and the Queen on the postage stamps.
邮票上还印有英国女王
But Gibraltar is also the southern gateway to Spain.
但直布罗陀也是西班牙的南方门户
A short boat trip from Africa leads straight here.
从非洲乘一小会儿船便能抵达此地
I'm standing at the very top of the rock of Gibraltar.
我站在直布罗陀巨岩上的极高处
And I'm looking right over the straits.
我往海峡那边望去
Those mountains are the Atlas Mountains.
那些山脉便是阿特拉斯山脉
And Gibraltar itself, the name derives from the Arabic,
而直布罗陀这个名字  便衍生自阿拉伯语
Jabal Al-Tariq, the Mountain of Tariq.
"加巴尔塔里克"  塔里克之山
And it's named after Tariq Bin-Ziyad,
命名者为塔里克·伊本·齐亚德
who governed nearby Tangiers in Morocco
他是摩洛哥丹吉尔附近的一名总督
on behalf of the distant Umayyad Caliph of Damascus.
代表着远方大马士革的倭马亚哈里发
In April 711, he raised an army
711年4月  他拉起了一支军队
of 7,000 Arabs and Berbers.
共有7000名阿拉伯人和柏柏尔人
And with his favourite beautiful slave girl by his side,
他身边带着最爱的美女奴隶
they embarked on rafts and crossed the straits to land in Europe.
他们乘上木筏  越过海峡  登陆欧洲
Islam had arrived in the West.
伊斯兰来到了西方
They carried all before them.
他们将横扫前方
The divided Visigoths were overwhelmed.
分崩离析的西哥特人招架不住
Some converted to Islam, others fled North.
他们有些人改信伊斯兰  有些逃往北方
The fate of Julian, said to have invited in the Muslims,
朱利安据说被穆斯林请了过去
is unknown.
但下落不明
The Muslim invaders would build a culture
穆斯林入侵者将建起的文化
that outshone its European neighbours in wealth and magnificence.
在财富和华丽上都会胜过欧洲邻国
Their legacy infuses everything in Southern Spain.
他们的遗产将渗入到西班牙南部的一切中
And modern Spanish is still full of Arab words.
现代的西班牙语里还有众多的阿拉伯词汇
For example,
举个例子
the Spanish word for oil, aceite,
西班牙语的 "油"  aceite
is based on the Arabic al-zayt for olive juice.
便来源于阿拉伯语 "al-zayt"  意为 橄榄汁
Many words the Spanish think of as their own today
现在许多西班牙人认为是自己语言的词汇
are in fact Arabic.
其实都是源自阿拉伯语
The Arabic name for the river that runs north through Andalusia,
这条阿拉伯名的河流正向北流经安达卢西亚
the al-wadi al-kabir, or great river,
阿尔-瓦德-阿尔-卡比尔  意为 大河
has not changed much.
至今变化不大
The Guadalquivir.
瓜达尔基维尔河
Remember those amphorae
还记得之前的双耳土罐吗
that had to be thrown away after being used just once or twice?
用了一两次后就得丢弃的双耳土罐
Well now, the Arabs with their typical cultural sophistication,
现在  文化向来复杂的阿拉伯人
would crack the problem of the domestic receptacle.
将会解决双耳土罐的使用次数问题
They glazed the inside of their vases.
他们往土罐内壁上釉
Now they could be used again and again.
于是它们就能多次使用了
An early case of domestic re-cycling.
这可算是早期的家庭循环再用
The Muslim conquerors wanted to keep Spain for themselves.
穆斯林征服者想要把西班牙牢握手中
Yet they owed allegiance to a far-off master.
然而他们效忠于一位远方的主人
The Umayyad Caliphs ruled more like magnificent Roman Emperors
倭马亚的哈里发们更像是华丽的罗马皇帝
than ascetic Islamists.
而非清寡的穆斯林
In 750 AD,
公元750年
they were challenged by descendents of Mohammed's uncle.
他们受到了默罕默德叔叔后裔的挑战
The Umayyads, Caliphs ruling from Damascus,
坐镇大马士革的倭马亚哈里发们
were overthrown by the more rigorous and severe fundamentalists
被更为虔诚严厉的原教旨主义者推翻了
led by the Abbasid family.
取而代之的是阿拔斯王朝
All the Umayyads were invited to a dinner in Damascus.
他们在大马士革设宴邀请所有倭马亚家族成员
In the middle of the banquet, all of them were massacred
然后在宴会上把他们全杀了
and their bodies preserved and stored in an underground chamber.
并把他们的尸体全都保存在一间地下室里
With each one labelled on their toes with their names.
每具尸体的脚趾上都挂有各自的姓名牌
Only one escaped.
只有一人幸免于难
His name was Prince Abd Al-Rahman.
他就是王子 阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼
He was 19, tall, handsome, red-haired.
他时年19岁  高挑英俊  有头红发
In a story really worthy of a Hollywood action movie, he escaped.
他脱逃而出的故事都可以拍一部好莱坞动作片了
The most wanted man in the Islamic world
他是伊斯兰世界的头号通缉犯
hunted by Abassid assassins
阿拔斯的杀手们紧追不舍
all the way across North Africa.
跟他一路横跨北非
At one point, the assassins got so close,
曾经一度  杀手们十分逼近他了
that he had to hide under
于是他不得不躲在
the skirts of an attractive female cousin.
一位迷人的女性表亲的裙底
The Abbasids moved the capital from Damascus
阿拔斯王朝把首都从大马士革
to their new city of Baghdad,
迁到了新城巴格达
which was even further from their most distant province, Spain.
这就离已是最远省份的西班牙还要更远了
For six years, Abd Al-Rahman - or Rach man - travelled westwards,
六年来  阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼一路向西
amassing supporters,
并聚拢支持者
convinced he could use his charisma to found his own kingdom.
他坚信能靠个人魅力来建立自己的王国
In September 755, he landed near Malaga.
755年9月  他登陆了马拉加附近
His followers awaited him there, a retinue of just 300.
他的跟随者已经在此等候  虽然只是300人的扈从
He headed north, towards Cordoba -
他向北朝着科尔多瓦行进
once the Roman capital - to face the Abbasids and their supporters.
那里曾是罗马首都  他要面对阿拔斯及其支持者们
This Damascene Prince swept all before him
这位大马士革王子仅靠少数骑兵
with just a handful of horsemen.
便一往无前
The final showdown was on the Guadalquivir River.
最后的决战在瓜达尔基维尔河上
Abd Al-Rahman, with just 700 men, smashed the forces of his enemies.
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼仅靠700人  便横扫敌军
And he then devised a special gift for the Abassid Caliph in Baghdad
然后他给巴格达的阿拔斯哈里发送了一份特殊礼物
who'd murdered his entire family.
以报家族灭顶之仇
He sealed a basket and sent it to the Caliph.
他用篮子装好封上  然后寄给了哈里发
When the monarch there in Baghdad opened it in front of his court,
当巴格达的君主在朝堂上打开礼物时
he shrieked in horror.
他惊恐大叫
It was a basket of severed heads.
篮子里装了好几颗人头
Abd Al-Rahman was a true Umayyad.
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼是位真正的倭马亚人
A tolerant Muslim and a magnificent builder,
他是宽容的穆斯林和伟大的建筑者
who would now create a paradise in Spain.
现在他将在西班牙建立一片天堂
A kingdom of prosperity, culture, harmony.
那将是个繁荣和谐  文化兴盛的王国
Abd Al-Rahman made his capital here in Cordoba,
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼定都于科尔多瓦这儿
where he created a great city of noble buildings
他在这建起的大城有着高贵的建筑
and lush gardens
有着葱郁的花园
to remind him of Damascus.
就像他的大马士革一样
But he never forgot, never ceased missing
但他难以忘怀  不停思念的
his home city, his Syria.
则是他的家乡 叙利亚
And he wrote a poignant poem
他还写了一首凄美的诗
to a palm tree of Cordoba.
以献给科尔多瓦的一棵棕榈树
He said,
他写道
"You too are a stranger here, sprung from foreign soil."
君亦他乡客  万里起繁叶
And he added, "I too am far from home."
我自飘零人  何处是归家
But he was now a monarch,
但现在他是君主了
yet he never forgot
他也一直没忘记
that he'd been a fugitive on the run for so many years.
自己流亡多年  逃避追捕
And he had a wonderfully earthy sense of humour.
他有着奇妙朴实的幽默感
He was visited by his attractive female cousin,
他的美貌表妹来访
up whose skirt he'd hidden from Abassid assassins.
他曾经躲在人家裙底逃避阿拔斯杀手
She used to tease him. "You hid under my skirt," she'd say.
她逗他说  你曾经还躲在我的裙底下呢
And he'd reply,
他答道
"Fragrant as you are,
你那么香气芬芳
"it was very stifling and stuffy up there."
在你下面都快喘不过气来了
One of the wonders of the Western world
西方世界的一大奇景
lies behind this golden doorway.
就在这道金门后面
This was the royal entrance,
这是皇室入口
reached by a covered passageway from the palace.
经由一条封闭通道通向王宫
Sealed up for centuries,
不过封门了几个世纪后
today, the way in is round the corner.
今天的入口则在角落里
In 786, Abd Al-Rahman started to build Cordoba's Great Mosque
786年  阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼开始建造科尔多瓦的
or Mezquita.
大清真寺
This would be his masterpiece.
这将是他的代表杰作
As more and more converted to Islam,
随着越来越多人改信伊斯兰
the Mezquita was expanded again and again over the centuries.
几世纪来  大清真寺一直在不断扩建
Its mihrab, or prayer niche,
寺内的米哈拉布  也叫祈祷壁龛
traditionally faces Mecca.
依照传统  朝向麦加
The Mezquita has 850 columns
大清真寺有850根列柱
made of granite and marble.
由花岗岩和大理石制成
A system of two-tiered pillars has been created,
双层柱支撑体系建立了起来
a forest of supports using Visigothic columns as a base.
这是以西哥特柱子为基础的支撑柱林
The conquering faith commandeering the ruins of the old
征服者以其意志征用老旧遗址
to build the new.
加以新建
Even the horseshoe arch adopted by Islam
甚至伊斯兰所用的马蹄形卷拱
may have been of Visigothic design.
可能也源于西哥特时代的设计
Now Cordoba became a cosmopolitan metropolis.
现在的科尔多瓦成了座国际性大都会
Arab scientists, true heirs to the Ancient Greeks,
阿拉伯科学家们是古希腊人的真正继任者
made astounding advances unknown to the brutish West.
野蛮的西方对他们的非凡成就却一无所知
Scholars, architects, poets, astrologers
学者  建筑师  诗人  占星家
gathered at the glittering Umayyad court.
集聚在耀眼的倭马亚宫廷
One man stood out.
其中一人脱颖而出
His name was Ali Ibn Nafi.
他就是阿里·伊本·纳菲
Ibn Nafi was a star, a famous singer-songwriter
伊本·纳菲是颗明星  他是著名的歌手和词人
who became an international trendsetter and dandy,
他成了国际性的潮流引领者和花花公子
an aficionado of style and pleasure.
是时尚和欢乐的狂热爱好者
There's something very modern about him, not unlike a rock star.
他很有现代的元素  不是像摇滚明星那样
A sort of cross between Beau Brummell and Mick Jagger.
而是有点儿像花花公子和摇滚巨星的结合体
Born in Baghdad, he was half Kurdish, half African.
他生于巴格达  有一半库尔德血统  一半非洲血统
Hence his nickname, the Blackbird.
因此他的绰号叫做 黑鸟
He had sung for the Caliphs in Baghdad.
他曾在巴格达为哈里发献唱
But when he came here to Cordoba, he really became famous.
但他来到科尔多瓦后  他真正成了巨星
He was best friends with the Crown Prince.
他是王子的最好朋友
He promoted asparagus from a weed to a delicacy.
他把芦笋从杂草变为了佳肴
He invented the modern three-course meal.
他发明了现代三道菜的正餐形式
Everyone wanted to look like him, dress like him, sound like him.
每个人都想看起来像他  穿起来像他  听起来像他
Everyone wanted to be like Ibn Nafi.
每个人都想像伊本·纳菲一样
I've come to watch a flamenco show.
我来观看弗拉门戈舞
This most Spanish of art forms can trace its roots
这一最具西班牙风情的舞蹈的起源
back to Ibn Nafi's musical vision.
可追溯到伊本·纳菲对音乐的想法
At its heart is a special technique for playing the guitar.
舞蹈核心是一种弹奏吉他的特殊技巧
Juan Antonio Martinez is professor of guitar
安东尼奥·马蒂内兹是一位吉他专家
at the Ibn Nafi Conservatory in Cordoba.
他就在科尔多瓦的伊本·纳菲音乐学院里
这所学校就是以他命名的
他是一位从巴格达来的吟游歌者
还创建了欧洲的第一所音乐学校
So what was Ibn Nafi's influence?
那么伊本·纳菲还有哪些影响呢
他给我们带来了乌得琴
之前他的老师纳斯里已在琴上加入了第五根弦
从而改变了它的弹奏方法
后来全欧洲都跟着再加一条弦
他改变了音乐的演唱和弹奏方式
所以现在弗拉门戈舞的吉他才会这样弹
So, is there a direct line from Ibn Nafi's oud
所以伊本·纳菲的乌得琴一脉相传至
all the way to the modern Spanish Flamenco guitar?
现代西班牙的弗拉门戈舞的吉他吗
是的  尤其是改变了音阶的调
最重要的可能是右手的用法变了
他们用野鸡羽毛来做类似拨弦片的功用
这是弗拉门戈独有的  叫做alzapua连音
其中要用大拇指上下弹奏
这是非常现代化的
So, now will you show us on the actual guitar?
现在你能用真的吉他演示一下吗
Si. Thank you.
可以  谢谢
现在所有的弗拉门戈乐手都这样弹
现在的吉他手这样扫弦使旋律变奏
The culture of Al-Andalus is deeply buried
安达卢斯的文化深埋于
in what became Spanish culture.
后来的西班牙文化之中
Yet Islamic tolerance can be a little exaggerated.
不过伊斯兰也没那么宽宏大量
Islam was supreme.
伊斯兰是至高无上的
Jews and Christians were only free to worship if they paid a special tax
犹太人和基督徒只有在缴纳特定赋税后才有信仰自由
and always recognised Muslim mastery.
并且总得接受穆斯林的掌控
And yet there were those, of course, who resented the supremacy of Islam.
当然也有一些人不满于穆斯林的称霸
Eulogius of Cordoba led a movement of radical Christians
科尔多瓦的欧洛吉亚领导激进基督徒发起运动
who actually sought martyrdom
他不畏殉教
by publicly insulting the Prophet Mohammed.
且公开侮辱了先知穆罕默德
Eulogious was duly arrested and tried and then beheaded.
欧洛吉亚自然遭到逮捕和审判  最后被斩首
The headless trunk of his body was tossed onto the river bank
他的无头残躯被抛弃河边
to be feasted upon by dogs.
让野狗们饱餐了一顿
In the writings he left behind, Eulogius quoted the Bible
欧洛吉亚留下了著作  并引用了圣经
and he left an ominous message.
留下了不详的信息
"Follow my example," he said,
他写道 "追随我的足迹吧"
"because I follow the example of Christ."
"因为我追随的是基督的足迹"
Religious co-existence would prove to be a challenging idea for Spain.
宗教共存将是西班牙的一大挑战
In 912, Abd Al-Rahman III,
912年  阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼三世
aged just 21,
时年仅21岁
succeeded to the throne of Cordoba.
他登上了科尔多瓦的王位
The greatest of the Umayyads,
他是倭马亚最伟大君主
he created paved streets, public lighting,
他铺设道路  建立公共照明
and collected a library of half a million books.
还搜集50万书籍创设图书馆
Cordoba under Abd Al-Rahman was one of the biggest,
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼治下的科尔多瓦是
richest and most diverse cities in all of Europe.
欧洲最大 最富有 最多元化的城市之一
Only Constantinople was its equal
只有君士坦丁堡可相提并论
and it may have had several hundred thousand people living in it.
城内估计有好几十万人口
At the same time, London and Paris had just 10-15,000 inhabitants.
同时期的伦敦和巴黎只有1万到1.5万居民
They were just glorified villages.
就只是大一点的村庄而已
Just outside Cordoba,
在科尔多瓦城外
these ruins display Abd Al-Rahman's ambition.
这些遗址展示了阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼的雄心
In 929, he declared himself The Caliph.
在929年  他自立为哈里发
Islam was divided between the Abassid Caliph in Baghdad
伊斯兰现在除了有巴格达的阿拔斯哈里发
and a new Fatimid Caliph in North Africa.
还有北非的新的法蒂玛哈里发
It was time for the Umayyads to show their power.
倭马亚是时候展示实力了
To project his authority as commander of the faithful,
为了显示自己是宗教领袖
as political and religious ruler,
是政治和宗教上的统治者
the Caliph of the West created this long-forgotten paradise
西方的哈里发建了这座久被遗忘的
of power and faith.
权力和信仰的天堂
It lay hidden for 900 years.
它曾埋于地下900年
Abd Al-Rahman moved his court to this vast hillside complex.
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼将宫廷迁至这座依山而建的大宫殿
Its grandeur was the architectural version of his own status
如此壮观的建筑正是他作为哈里发和征服者的
as Caliph and conqueror.
地位的体现
Only one thing really mattered to him,
只有一件事对他来说是重要的
the plenitude and panoply of his own power.
那就是对其权力的丰盛展示
And that's why he built this amazing complex.
所以他才会建造这座惊人的宫殿
The Medinat Al-Zahara, the dazzling palace.
麦地那-阿沙哈拉宫  一座耀眼的宫殿
And it really does dazzle.
它也确实足够耀眼
This was political headquarters, military command centre,
这里是政治总部和军事指挥中心
spectacular showpiece and pleasure palace.
也是壮丽的展品和享乐的宫殿
The palace wasn't only intimidating to those inside.
这座宫殿不仅使里面的人望而生畏
It commanded views for miles around along the river valley.
沿着河谷的方圆数英里内也都能看到它
The ideal majestic fortress for a vigilant, paranoid monarch
这是警惕而又偏执的君主的理想的壮丽城堡
like Abd Al-Rahman.
阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼便是如此
At heart,
在内心中
this man was a ferocious and thin-skinned tyrant.
他是位凶残和小气的暴君
He was stout, blonde, stunted,
他肥胖粗壮  金发碧眼  身材矮小
and his legs were so short, that he had to have special stirrups made.
因为他的腿太短  所以马镫都要专门打造
And he didn't take kindly to rejection.
拒绝他的人可不会有好果子吃
He kept two harems here, one of boys and one of girls.
他在这里建了两座后宫  男女宠各住一座
When a girl resisted his advances, he had her face burnt off.
有个女子拒绝了他的追求  他便将她的脸烧毁
When a boy did the same, he was dismembered.
有个男子也拒绝了他  于是就被肢解了
He was Pelagius of Cordoba, who was later canonised.
后来那男子被封圣为科尔多瓦的佩拉吉乌斯
And somewhere here in this palace he kept a menagerie,
他还在宫殿里的某处建了个动物园
a zoo of lions.
里面都是狮子
And if he didn't like you,
要是你惹到了他
he fed you to them.
他就把你扔去喂狮子
The hanging gardens were legendary.
它的空中花园是有名的传奇
Water for the sunken pools was pumped all the way
泳池里的水源源不断地
from the Guadalquivir river.
从瓜达尔基维尔河抽来
These waterways even supplied one of the world's first water closets.
这些水道甚至还供水给世界上第一个水厕
Here in an obscure corner of the Medinat Al-Zahara
在阿沙哈拉宫的一个小角落里
is an impressive piece of modern Arab technology.
有着阿拉伯现代技术的惊人之作
It's down here.
就在下面这里
Now let me show you this.
我来给你展示一下
This is an early, rather primitive bidet.
这是一个早期的还很原始的坐浴盆
You can see there's running water.
这里会有流动的水流
What we're looking at here is in fact one of the first examples
我们现在所看到的其实是欧洲的
of a European flushing lavatory.
第一个冲水厕所
The courtiers of the Caliph lived here in comfort and hygiene
哈里发的臣子于此舒适和卫生地生活着
at a time when Londoners and Parisians
而同时代的伦敦人和巴黎人
were mired in a miasma of stinking filth.
还都过得乌烟瘴气的
The complex was sacked in the early part of the 11th century,
这座宫殿在11世纪早期被洗劫一空
so completely, that for many centuries, people doubted
以至于许多世纪来的人们都怀疑
that the Medinat Al-Zahara had ever existed.
麦地那-阿沙哈拉宫是否真的存在过
It was only rediscovered in 1911.
直到1911年它才被发掘出来
And Abd Al-Rahman's buried secrets are still being revealed
而现代的人们还正在发掘阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼的
to the modern world.
被掩埋的秘密
It's said that he named it after his favourite concubine
据说他用自己最爱的嫔妃的名字来命名这宫殿
but he doesn't really strike me as much of a romantic.
不过我觉得他可不怎么像是浪漫的人
Besides, he wasn't spoilt for choice.
此外  他也没什么选择余地
He had 6,000 girls here in his harem.
他的宫里有6000名女子
Historian Simon Barton has written a book about the practice
历史学家 西蒙·巴顿 写的一本书讲到了
of taking concubines.
如何选择嫔妃
It was all about good looks
说到底就是外貌选美
and apparently it was said that the Umayyad Caliphs
明显有说法是这位倭马亚哈里发
were predisposed by nature to prefer blondes.
天性更喜欢金发女郎
Now that's interesting. Where did these blondes come from?
这就有趣了  哪里来的金发女郎呢
There were markets in Northern France, in the Mediterranean.
在法国北部和地中海都有市场的
We have Muslim slave merchants
里面有买卖穆斯林奴隶的
but also Jews heavily involved in trafficking,
犹太人也是买卖的重头
particularly women and children across Europe.
还有尤其是欧洲的女人和小孩
And if one of these concubines,
如果他的嫔妃中有人是
who had been bought as powerless slaves,
被买来作为无权的奴隶
became the mother of a future monarch, a future caliph,
然后成了未来君主  未来哈里发的母亲
they could become vastly powerful.
那么他们的权力就十分的大了
That's absolutely true.
确实如此
In fact, all the emirs and caliphs of the Umayyad dynasty
事实上  倭马亚王朝的所有埃米尔和哈里发
were born to slave concubines.
都是奴隶嫔妃所生的
And they were said to have likewise blonde hair, blue eyes.
据说他们都是金发碧眼的
The advantage of a concubine is that it functions
这种嫔妃的作用就像是
as a dynastic defence mechanism.
王朝的一种防御机制
It means that unlike a wife's family,
这就意味着不会有妃嫔家族
which can get involved in the politics of a dynasty,
来参与王朝的政治
the concubine as a slave
奴隶出身的嫔妃
who's been uprooted from her home land,
她们的家乡在万里之外
will have no vested interest in the dynasty itself.
在王朝内部也没有既得利益
It was a way of keeping the dynasty secure.
这是一种保障王朝安全的方法
So, actually, it's much more about power than sex?
所以背后更多的是政治  而性不那么重要吗
Absolutely.
完全正确
The system required a strong Caliph at the top.
这个体制要求强大的哈里发立于顶端
And when the rules were broken,
而当规则被破坏了
the Caliphate fell apart.
哈里发也就倒台了
In 976, the succession of a child, Caliph Hisham II,
976年  一名孩童继任哈里发  希沙姆二世
revealed its fragility.
暴露了体制的脆弱
He was still a boy growing up under the tutelage of his mother,
他还是个在母亲监护下成长的孩子
Subh, a former concubine.
苏卜  曾经的嫔妃
She sidelined Hisham, her own son,
她撇开自己的儿子 希沙姆
and opened the doors of power to forces outside the Umayyad dynasty.
并向倭马亚王朝之外的势力打开权力的大门
She appointed her new lover as Grand Vizier, prime minister.
她任命自己的新欢为总理大臣
His name was Al-Mansur, the Victorious,
他名叫曼苏尔  意为胜利
and he was one of the most brilliant, ruthless
他是整个哈里发政权里最为
and extraordinary characters of the entire Caliphate.
聪明  无情和非凡的人物
He launched 57 raids of holy war against the Christian North,
他发动了57场圣战来反对北方的基督徒
burning and pillaging and looting.
对其烧杀抢掠
Here in Cordoba, he burned the civilised cultured libraries
在科尔多瓦这儿  他烧毁了之前倭马亚哈里发们所建的
of the Umayyad Caliphs before him.
象征文明文化的图书馆
In his raids in the North, he destroyed all he found
在北伐途中  他目之所及  无不将其摧毁
in order to fund the building of mosques and palaces here.
搜刮的钱财就用来资助这里的清真寺和宫殿
In 997, his raids reached their climax
在997年  他的征伐达到了顶峰
when he sacked Santiago de Compostela.
那时他在洗劫圣地亚哥-德孔波斯特拉
The doors and the bells of its churches were brought back
那里的教堂的门和钟都被带回了
in triumph to Cordoba, on the backs of Christian slaves.
而搬运门钟  凯旋归往科尔多瓦的正是基督徒奴隶
Ironically, Al-Mansur was too successful.
讽刺的是  曼苏尔实在是太成功了
His triumphs hollowed out and undermined the Caliphate.
他的一系列胜利反而掏空和侵蚀了哈里发政权
He promoted himself as a quasi-Caliph
他使自己成为准哈里发
and founded his own semi-royal dynasty
并通过娶回一位基督徒公主
by marrying a Christian princess.
从而建立了自己的准王朝
Al-Mansur's sons lacked
曼苏尔的儿子们没有父亲的
his irrepressible drive,
那种一往无前的动力
his talent and his restraint.
那种才智和克制
When they undermined the legitimacy of the Caliph,
他们破坏了哈里发的合法性
the regime disintegrated.
于是政权崩解了
First, he was succeeded by one son, then he was assassinated.
起先他的长子接任官职  而后被暗杀了
But then came the preposterous popinjay Sanchuelo,
但后继的弟弟是个装腔作势者 山朱勒
who tried to make himself a Caliph.
他想自己当哈里发
The entire kingdom fell apart.
整个王国分崩离析了
There died the glory of Al-Andalus.
安达卢斯的光辉也随之黯淡
In 1031, 30 years after Al-Mansur's death, the Caliphate collapsed.
1031年  曼苏尔死后30年  哈里发政权倒台了
Al-Andalus broke down into little city states,
安达卢斯分裂成了几个小城邦
ruled by their princes, like medieval barons in the West.
由西方的中世纪贵族那样的首领统治着
The Great Mosque of Cordoba, built by the first Abd Al-Rahman
科尔多瓦大清真寺  由初任阿卜杜勒·拉赫曼草创
and expanded by Al-Mansur,
也经过曼苏尔的扩建
still exists.
它至今犹存
We can still admire its scale and beauty.
我们依然可以欣赏其规模和壮丽
When it later fell to the Christians, they didn't destroy it.
它后来落入基督徒之手  但未被摧毁
They built a cathedral amidst the Mezquita.
他们在这清真寺里建了座教堂
Even today, people in Cordoba talk
即使在今天  科尔多瓦人也会说
of going to mass in the Mosque.
要去大清真寺里做弥撒
I'm travelling to Granada now for my last stop.
我正在前往我的终点站 格拉纳达
I'm following the story of one man, who despite not being a Muslim,
我要追寻的是一个故事的主角  他虽然不是穆斯林
rose to the top in 11th-century Islamic Spain.
却在11世纪伊斯兰的西班牙中如日中天
And who did so at a moment
故事主角所处的时代
when Islamic Spain itself was in the grip of change.
正是伊斯兰西班牙处于变革洪流的时代
The city of Granada owes its name to both its Jewish and Muslim roots.
格拉纳达的名字来源于它的犹太人和穆斯林渊源
The Jews called it the City of Pomegranates.
犹太人把它叫做石榴之城
And the Arab word for pomegranate is gr'nata.
而阿拉伯语中的石榴就是格拉纳达
The Emirate of Granada was one of the smaller principalities
格拉纳达酋长国正是哈里发解体后
that came after the Caliphate.
分出来的一个小公国
This, its most celebrated attraction,
这里是它最著名的景点
is part of its later history.
也是其后历史的一部分
I'll be coming back here in the next episode.
我在下一集里还会来到这儿
To explore its splendour
来探索它的壮丽
and see some of its lesser-known gems.
来观赏它的一些鲜为人知的珍宝
This amazing building is now famous as
这座惊人的建筑如今是著名的
the Alhambra Palace of Granada.
格拉纳达的阿尔罕布拉宫
But 300 years before it was built,
但在它建成300年前
this was the site of the palace
这里也是一座皇宫
of one of the most extraordinary Jewish leaders in Spanish history
其主人是西班牙史上最非凡的犹太领袖之一
and in fact, one of the most extraordinary statesmen
他实际上也是这半岛上所有故事中
in all of the peninsula's story.
最为非凡的政治家之一
His name was Samuel Ibn Naghrillah.
他名叫塞缪尔·伊本·奈格瑞拉
He started off as a spice merchant in Cordoba.
他原本是科尔多瓦的香料商人
He moved here and became the advisor to the Berber rulers
他来到这里成了柏柏尔人的顾问
of the principality of Granada.
后者统治着格拉纳达公国
When he backed the right candidate for the throne,
他拥护正确的候选人登上了王位
Samuel became not only the leader of the Jewish Community
塞缪尔不仅成了犹太社区的领袖
but the Grand Vizier, the prime minister,
还当上了总理大臣
and the Commander in Chief of the Granadan army.
以及格拉纳达主力军队的指挥官
In war, he commanded and won victories.
在战争中  他指挥赢得了胜利
In peace, he was leader of the Jewish community,
和平之时  他则领导着犹太人社区
he wrote works of Jewish philosophy,
他著有犹太哲学作品
he was a rabbi,
他是一名拉比
and above all, he was a poet.
并且还是一位诗人
His poetry is astonishing even in English translation.
他的诗歌即使翻成了英文也仍震撼人心
But he wrote in Hebrew and in Arabic.
不过他用希伯来语和阿拉伯语写作
He wrote love poems.
他写过爱情诗
Love poems to beautiful girls,
他写情诗送给美丽的女子
to wine,
送给酒
to boys
送给男子
and to the excitement of victory in war.
送给战争中激动人心的胜利
Here in Granada, a group of Naghrillah enthusiasts
在格拉纳达这儿  一群奈格瑞拉的爱好者
are gathering to hear some of his poetry.
聚集起来准备听他的一些诗歌
塞缪尔·奈格瑞拉
《我如何帮助智者》
你听过我是如何帮助
你听过我是如何帮助智者的吗
老者们是正在走向完满吗
那么敬畏上帝的小男孩们呢
看着多美美好  多么年轻啊
那么他们的兄弟呢
我订好了一片庭院准备开聚会  我说
"我们来过上美美的一天吧"
"离别将至  我们饮酒纪念"
"停杯者将为悲伤所扰"
"友谊和精力相伴"
"死亡与离别相随"
所以他们坐上这红色垫子
In this poem, Naghrillah describes how wisdom
在这首诗中  奈格瑞拉描述了智慧是如何
comes from the knowledge we're not here forever.
来自于我们所永远不能习得的知识中的
然后他们饮酒  倾述秘密
而我们安适自在
心旷神怡
In 1056, Samuel Naghrillah died
1056年  塞缪尔·奈格瑞拉逝世
but he was succeeded by his son Joseph as Grand Vizier of Granada.
他的儿子 约瑟夫 继任为格拉纳达的总理大臣
Joseph was only 20 but he can't have been a fool
约瑟夫年仅20岁  但可不是个愣头青
because he ruled for ten years.
因为他已有10年的统治经验
It was quite traditional for Grand Viziers to be succeeded by their sons
传统上常有总理大臣传位给儿子的
and even to found little mini-dynasties.
甚至建起小型王朝也不足为奇
But there was a problem.
但还有个问题
The Naghrillahs were Jews.
奈格瑞拉家族是犹太人
Now this Jewish potentate seemed an enemy within
现在这个犹太当权者似乎是
from a dynasty of interlopers.
这一外来王朝的内部敌人
In 1066, a date as resonant for the Jews of Granada
1066年  对于格拉纳达的犹太人是难忘的
as it was for King Harold,
正如同一年的哈罗德国王
the Saxon King of England,
这位英格兰的撒克逊国王一样
something snapped.
有些事要变化了
A mob came to Joseph's palace,
一群暴民来到约瑟夫的宫殿
close to the Alhambra,
就在阿尔罕布拉宫附近
and dragged him out.
他被逼了出来
They chased him through the streets.
他们追他到街上
He was unable to escape.
他没能逃脱
When the mob finally caught up with Joseph Naghrillah,
暴民们追上约瑟夫·奈格瑞拉的地方
it was right here.
就是在这里
They lynched him and then went on a killing spree,
他们私刑处死了他  并发起了一场大屠杀
massacring 4,000 Jews.
屠杀了4000名犹太人
As for Joseph, they crucified him
约瑟夫被他们钉在十字架上
right here beside this magnificent city gate.
就立在这座宏伟的城门边上
The crucifixion of Joseph Naghrillah in Granada marked
约瑟夫·奈格瑞拉于格拉纳达被钉死在十字架上
the beginning of the end of religious pluralism in Muslim Spain.
开启了穆斯林西班牙宗教多元化的终结
The Naghrillahs were not the first Jewish Grand Viziers
奈格瑞拉不是伊斯兰世界里的首位
in the Islamic world.
犹太裔总理大臣
Yet the confidence of the Caliphate,
然而哈里发政权的自信
necessary for such broad-mindedness,
以及宗教宽容的必要性
was past.
不复存在了
Over 400 years, Spain would tear itself apart.
400多年中  西班牙将四分五裂
Next time, how the Christian Kings of the North struck back,
下一集  北方的基督教国王如何卷土重来
conquering all of Spain for the cross.
为十字架而征服全西班牙
How Spain purified its blood in a vicious Inquisition,
西班牙如何用恶毒的宗教裁判所来净化血脉
catching even some of my own family in its net.
甚至抓捕了我的一些家族先祖
Oh, my God! So this is his death sentence?
我的天啊  这是他的死刑判决书吗
It's just heartbreaking.
我的心要碎了
And how Christopher Columbus set sail
还有克里斯托弗·哥伦布如何扬帆起航
to discover a rich American empire.
发现富饶的美洲帝国
If this story has inspired you
如果这段历史对你有所启发
and you'd like to find out more,
如果你想获取更多知识的话
go to the address given on screen
你可以打开屏幕下方的网址
and follow the links to The Open University.
从网站里面访问英国开放大学